≪ワンハンドトス
A one-handed set?
(一同)よしゃ
All right!
(滝ノ上)
同点土壇場で追いついた
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
They're tied! They caught up in the eleventh hour!
(ハルカ)なんだけこれ
(ユウコ)デュス
What is this called again?
Deuce!
(日向･影山)
≪先に２点差つけた方が
Whoever takes a two-point lead first...
勝つ
wins!
Episode Twenty-four:
"Lonely King" No More
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
(烏野一同)よしゃ
All right!
オオオオ青城
Oh, oh, oh! Seijou!
(青城応援団)青城
Seijou!
Rule the Court
(部員たち)オオオオ青城
Oh, oh, oh! Seijou!
(青城応援団)青城
Seijou!
(部員たち)オオオオ青城
Oh, oh, oh! Seijou!
出していくぞ
Don't panic! Get out there and make some noise!
Yessir!
国見ちゃんいけるね
(国見)はい
Are you good to go, Kunimi?
Yes, sir.
Hey! You two are amazing!
(西谷)うおい
すげぇぞ日向影山
(影山飛雄)≪国見もあんなふうに
必死になてボルを追うのか
I didn't know Kunimi knew how to chase after a ball for dear life.
((最後まで追えよ
Don't stop chasing it halfway!
(日向翔陽)影山
は
Kageyama!
ブロド何回でも打つかんな
I'll do the broad jump as many times as it takes!
決まるまで
Until it works!
おお
Right.
(澤村)行くぞ
(一同)しゃ
Let's go!
Yes!
ピ
(縁下)流れはこちだ
Give us a good serve!
We have the momentum!
Give it all you've got, Tanaka!
(菅原)思い切り行け田中
(田中)しゃ行くぜ
Okay, here goes nothing!
I've got it!
(嶋田)ちょと乱れた
(滝ノ上)ブロクブロク
They're out of formation!
Center!
Block it!
(西谷)チャンスボル
We can score off this!
チャンスボル
Here's our chance!
もう一本
One more ball!
(渡)く
(岩泉)ナイスレシブ渡
Nice receive, Watari!
１０番戻んの速い
Number ten resets fast!
ナイスワンタチ
Nice block!
もういかい
One more time!
(岩泉)上がるて分かてて
フリにしてやる理由はねぇよ
I know you're getting the set,
so I ain't gonna leave you unmarked!
≪日向のジャンプ力が落ちてる
タイミング合わない
Hinata is tired and can't jump as high! The timing is off!
(３人)あ
(渡)う
Ow.
おお
ピ
All right!
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
(烏野一同)よしゃ
翔陽
Shouyou!
うおい今のは
日向に救われたなおい
Hey! Hinata just saved our butts!
今度は
(澤村)一気に取るぞ
This time...
We're rushing them!
(一同)おお
(滝ノ上)烏野が王手だ
Yeah!
...Karasuno gets to say "check."
(及川)
落ち着いて行こう取り返す
Keep calm. We'll take it back!
(一同)おう
ピ
Yessir!
(澤村)
田中もう一本ナイサ
Tanaka, serve up another one!
(渡)花巻さん
(花巻)しゃ
Hanamaki!
Yes!
ピ
(青城一同)しゃ
(嶋田)点数は同じでも
Aoba Jousai                   Karasuno
Yes!
The score may be tied,
青城がブレイクしないかぎり
but Karasuno still has the upper hand as long as Seijou doesn't score right now.
今度は烏野が
常に優位に立た状態
That being said...
(嶋田)
ここでまた及川のサブかよ
once again, Oikawa is serving at the worst time.
(２人)はぁはぁ
≪君らの思いどおりには
攻撃させない≫
I won't let you attack the way you want to.
≪勝つのは俺たちだ≫
We're winning this, not you.
≪もと高い舞台へ行く≫
We're moving on to a bigger stage.
Shiratorizawa                Kitagawa First
(及川)((今度こそ
I'm gonna humiliate Shiratorizawa instead!
白鳥沢へこましてやる))
≪この一本でアドバンテジを
We'll take the advantage back with this play!
Olé!
取り戻す≫
(東峰)西谷
Nishinoya!
ピ
ナイスジャジ西谷
Nice judgment call, Nishinoya!
Right.
(得点係)ミスた
及川がサブミスた
He flubbed it.
I can't believe Oikawa flubbed a serve.
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
また烏野のマチポイント
It's match point for Karasuno again.
あんだけ決めてたサブ
ミスるてことは
He has to be losing it big time to screw up the serves he's usually so good at!
Give us a good serve, Hinata!
かなり焦りがあるんじゃねぇか
ああさすがの及川も
Yeah, even Oikawa isn't invulnerable.
(２人)あ
これでチャラな
どちだて同じ１点だ
That evens the score.
A point is a point either way.
Iwaizumi, you're so cool!
(２人)岩泉さんかけ
(及川)岩ちゃんに負けた気分
Now I feel inferior to you.
お前は今までのいつ
俺に勝たんだ
Since when have you been superior to me?
(入畑)≪実際には
ブレイクかサイドアウトかで
In reality, there may very well be a significant difference between scoring on your serve or your opponent's serve.
Historically, I've always been superior!
Ow!
１点の重みは違うかもしれない
でも今それよりも重要なのは
岩泉の１点とひと言で
But the most important thing for now is that Iwaizumi's actions and words have kept the team from falling apart.
Okay, let's get that point.
Right!
チムが崩れるのを
免れたということ≫
青城一回も
全国行たことないて
Is it really true that Seijou has never made it to nationals?
うそじゃねぇの
全然崩れねぇ
They're such a solid team.
でも青城が追う立場なのは
変わんねぇ
Maybe, but in reality, they're still lagging behind.
体力的な消耗は一緒でも
Both teams are exhausted physically, but mentally, Seijou has to be way more exhausted.
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
精神的にきついのは
圧倒的に青城の方だ
Don't let them catch up, Karasuno!
逃げきれ烏野
Rule the Court
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
(ハルカ)うわぁ
Whoa!
They both passed thirty points!
３０点越えた
It's gotta be hard on both sides.
どちもきついな
けど
Yeah, but I get the feeling that Karasuno is barely keeping the ball in play.
烏野の方が
ギリギリで繋いでるて感じか
攻撃も
単調になてきてる気がする
Their attacks seem to be getting a little uninspired.
精神的にきついのは
青城の方なんだろうけど
Sure, Seijou has to be feeling the
psychological pressure worse, but...
(３人)及川君ナイサ
Oikawa, you can do it!
げ
今のでロテ１周か
Ugh! That put the rotation around full circle!
Give us a good one!
でもさきのサブミスも
まだ頭にあるだろうし
He'll be mindful of that serve he flubbed last time, so how will he handle it?
One point!
及川はどう出るかな
Oikawa, you'd better not be thinking about Ushiwaka during the match, or I'll clobber you one.
及川試合中に
ウシワカの顔ちらついてんなら
ぶ飛ばすからな
ギク
目の前の相手さえ
見えてないヤツが
Someone who's blind to the opponent in front of them can't beat the opponent that comes after them.
その先にいる相手を
倒せるもんかよ
そうだね
You're right.
一本で切る
うす
One point and he's gone!
Yessir!
(及川)返てくるﾁｬﾝｽﾎﾞｰﾙ
(花巻)オライ
It's coming back! We have a chance to score!
I've got it!
≪さき
ミスたばかて場面で
Considering how he messed up the last one,
I think that might be the greatest serve I've seen all day!
おそらく
今日見た中で最高のサブ
くそすまん
Shit, I'm sorry!
(東峰)あんなの上がるだけで
ありがたいつうの
Be grateful that you even got that up in the air!
≪落ち着け落ち着け
囮に飛びつかないように≫
Calm down! Calm down!
I've got it!
Don't jump at the decoy!
(東峰)≪速攻来るか
それともこの場面はやはり
Will it be a fast attack?
Or does this situation call for their ace?
Left!
エスか
レフト
≪逆サイド
≪また
The opposite side?!
Is it...
≪国見
Kunimi again?!
((国見囮だて分かてても
Kunimi!
You have to go in for the hit even if they know you're a decoy!
打つつもりで入てこいよ
((けど今のレフトに上がるて
相手にもバレバレだたじゃん))
But the opponent could obviously tell the ball was going left.
((ムダに疲れる必要ない))
Why waste the energy?
((お前うまいのに
なんで本気でやんないんだよ))
You're good at it, so why don't you ever take the sport seriously?
(国見)((常にがむしゃらなことが
イコル本気なのかよ))
So I'm not serious unless I'm constantly busting my balls?
う
(国見)チャンスボル
(渡)オライ
We can score here!
I've got it!
≪まだ余力が
He still has energy?!
(及川)((国見ちゃん
今囮に入るのサボたね
Kunimi, I just saw you slacking on your decoy work.
((うすみませ
((もうちょい上手にサボりなよね))
I'm s—
You'd better learn to be more sneaky or Mizoguchi will yell at you again.
((また溝口君に
どやされるよ))
(溝口)((国見ボケェ
Kunimi, you moron!
((効率よく燃費よく
常に冷静が
You're efficient, conservative, and always calm.
That's your secret weapon.
国見ちゃんの
裏の武器なんだからさ))
((でもその分
みんなが疲れた終盤に
Rest assured you'll make up for it by playing full throttle at the end when the rest of us are too tired to play.
がつり働いてもらうからね))
≪味方の１００％を
引き出してこそのセタ
A real setter gets every player on his team working at 100%!
≪どんな選手だろうとも
だよ
No matter who that player may be!
Got it?!
(２人)≪また１３番
Number thirteen again?!
(３人)≪フェイント
A diversion!
く
(武田)あ
Aoba Jousai                   Karasuno
(他校生)青城逆転した
Seijou made their comeback!
青城またマチポイント
Seijou has match point again!
Not only that, Oikawa still has the serve!
しかもサブはまだ及川
(青城応援団)あと１点あと１点
We were on the same team for three years, but I never saw...
≪３年間一緒のチムだた≫
≪けど試合中に
Good going.
普通に笑う国見を
今日初めて見た≫
Kunimi smile during a match like a normal player before.
Not bad!
Keep it up!
ちょとこのまま聞いて
≪何なんだあんた≫
Guys, wait a second. I need to say something.
Who are you?
How am I supposed to
≪あんたみたいな人に
どうやて太刀打ちすれば
compete with someone like you?
影山影山影山君
Kageyama?
Kageyama!
影山さん
Earth to Kageyama!
おいまさかビビてんのか
だせぇ
Hey, don't tell me you're getting spooked out. Talk about lame!
Whoa!
ふがしだ大王様が
王様よりすごいなんて
Th-Think about it! Obviously a great king is gonna be better than a king.
当然じゃんか名前的にも
That goes name-wise too!
絶対お前より
頭とかよさそうだし
Heck, he even looks smarter than you!
(澤村)すまん影山
My bad, Kageyama!
次絶対お前のとこへ
ボル返してみせる
I'll get the ball back to you the next time.
そしたらあとはいつもどおり
Then we'll play it like usual and do the attack you think is best.
お前がベストだと思う攻撃を
すればいい
(菅原)
影山迷てんじゃねぇぞ
Kageyama!
Quit second-guessing!
うちの連中は
What is everyone on our team?
ちゃんとみんな強い
They're good at what they do.
(月島)王様は大王様に
ビビちゃいましたかね
Do you think our king got spooked by the Great King?
(菅原)ふふ
(山口)ん
(菅原)大丈夫影山はもう
It's okay, 'cause Kageyama isn't a lonely king anymore.
孤独な王様じゃないからね
Haikyuu !!
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
Go for it! Go, go, go, go, Seijou!
(部員)行け
行け行け行け行け青城
Okay, bring it!
さ来い
来いや
Attack! Attack, attack, attack, attack, Seijou!
Bring it!
一本取るぞ
おお
We're getting that point!
Yeah!
(及川)ああ嫌だなぁ
Aw, yuck.
What a nuisance.
ほんと厄介
(岩泉)ナイサ
(及川)≪飛雄
Give us a good serve!
Tobio, you and your rapid rate of evolution
One point!
Now, bring it!
急速に進化するお前に
俺は負けるのかもしれないね
might have me beat.
(及川)≪でも
But...
Olé!
あ前
Front!
上がた
でも乱された速攻は使えない
It's up!
But they're not in formation!
They can't do a fast attack!
(繋心)≪どうしても身構えて
硬くなてしまうこの場面で
Just when the pressure of the situation has you too tense, a diversion comes for that tiny hole in your defense.
僅かな穴を狙たフェイント
勝ちをもぎ取るための
恐ろしいほどの冷静さ≫
The terrifyingly calm focus to rip victory from your grasp!
レフト
センタ
Left!
Center!
レフト
旭行け
Asahi, go!
(花巻)繋げ繋げ
(及川)岩ちゃん
Keep it in play!
Iwa!
う
It's up—
(武田)上があ
(岩泉)やれ金田一
Do it, Kindaichi!
You have me beat in both speed and reflexes. However...
(金田一)≪スピドも反射も
俺はお前に負けぱなしだ≫
≪でも
高さの真向勝負なら
負けねぇんだよ
In a head-on battle for height, I'm the best!
(他校生)上がた
おらぁ
It's up!
Get it!
オライ
(岩泉)金田一国見
I've got it!
Kindaichi! Kunimi!
(２人)はい
(東峰)レフト
Yes, sir!
Left!
≪今この位置
このタイミングこの角度で
Now!
This position!
This timing!
This angle!
≪ドンピシャ
It's bang-on!
(及川)≪飛雄
Tobio.
You and your rapid rate of evolution
急速に進化するお前に
might have me beat.
俺は負けるのかもしれないね≫
≪でも
But...
not today.
≪それは今日じゃない≫
Right on!
(一同)よしゃ
(繋心)あぁ
(部員)ナイスブロク
(部員)はははは
(部員)やたな
We did it!
(菅原)行こう
Let's go.
Yes!
(澤村)日向影山整列だ
Hinata, Kageyama. Time to line up.
キャプテンすみませ
(澤村)今のはミスじゃない
Captain, I'm sorry.
You didn't mess that up.
ミスじゃないから謝るな
No apology is required!
(一同)ありがとうございました
Thank you for the match!
(拍手)
((みんな
ちょとこのまま聞いて
Guys, wait a second. I need to say something.
次烏野に
速攻使えそうな場面があたら
The next opportunity Karasuno gets to use their fast attack,
飛雄は
必ず神業の方を使てくる
Tobio will definitely go for the superhuman version.
Keep that in mind.
頭に入れといて))
How did you know they'd go for
the superhuman attack in the end?
どうして最後のが
神業速攻だて分かた
飛雄が烏野のあのメンツの中で
進化したからだよ
I knew because Tobio evolved
alongside those team members.
あいつは
初めて信頼を覚え始めた
He's finally learning how to establish a rapport.
Aoba Jousai                    Karasuno
As the deuce dragged on, his mental and physical exhaustion peaked.
そして
デュスが続いて身も心も
疲労のピク
本当に追い詰められた土壇場
So, when his back was truly against the wall,
he was presented with the oh-so-vital opportunity.
そこへ与えられた
貴重なチャンス
At that specific time, the new Tobio...
そのとき今の飛雄の選択肢は
(及川)１つしかないんだよ
had only one option.
Form a line!
整列ありがとうございました
Thank you for the match!
(一同)ありがとうございました
(拍手)
お疲れ
いい試合だた
Well done!
That was a good match!
(澤村)集合
Gather 'round!
負けたときにさ
ん
When we lost,
いい試合だたよて
言われんのが嫌いだたよ
I hated it when someone told me it was a good match.
I was like, "But I lost!"
でも負けたじゃんてさ
But now that it's my turn to say something,
it's the only appropriate thing I can think to say.
を掛ける側になたとき
それ以外に妥当な言葉て
分かんねぇもんだな
あの最後の
Listen, that last block...
All right! Let's do this!
(泉石一同)しゃ
一本一本
すぐ撤収だ
次のチムのアプが始まる
We need to vacate.
The next team has to start warming up.
We'll cool down upstairs or outside.
クルダウンは上か外でやる
Senseki, fight!
(繋心)青城は少し時間空けてから
続けて準々決勝だ
Seijou will take a break and proceed to the quarterfinal.
Senseki, fight!
Yeah!
｢一人だけうまくても
勝てないんだよドンマイ｣て
Weren't you gonna console them by saying they couldn't win off the merits of just one player?
言てやるんじゃなかたけ
一人だけ強いわけじゃ
なかたじゃん烏野は
Karasuno wasn't a one-man team after all.
お前めんどくせぇな
ひどいな
You're a real pain in the ass.
That's mean!
２セト目のラスト
When Tobio read that I'd set it to you in the last play of the second set,
岩ちゃんへのトスを読まれたとき
飛雄が独裁の王様から
I knew he was changing from a dictator king to a decent king.
まともな王様に
なろうとしてるのが分かた
もし飛雄が
昔の独裁者のままだたとしても
Tobio still might've given the set to the small fry even if he was still a dictator,
ラストチビちゃんに
上げたかもしれないけど
so it was just a possibility at the time, and I didn't think it was a sure thing.
その場合は
可能性があるてだけで
絶対に上げるとまでは
思えなかた
俺の攻撃を読んでみせたことが
When he showed me he could read my attack,
it allowed me to turn the tables and read his attack.
今度は俺に攻撃を読まれることに
なちゃたわけだ
(岩泉)あの影山が
今やと他人への信頼を
So, our Kageyama has finally learned to trust others.
覚え始めたてわけか
ほんと
Tell me about it.
Nothing could be more of a nuisance.
厄介このうえないよね
ミティング始まる
The meeting's starting.
悪かた
Sorry about that.
最後完全に読まれた
He read me like a book.
Don't you dare apologize!
謝てんじゃねぇよ俺に
Don't make it sound like it was a mistake to set the ball to me!
俺に上げたのが
間違いだたみたいに言うな
(武田)ミティング
始まてしまいますよ
The meeting is about to start.
今日もすばらしい活躍でしたよ
二人とも
The both of you did a fabulous job today.
でも負けました
But we lost.
(武田)確かに負けました
でも実りある試合だたのでは
Yes, you lost.
But don't you think it was a productive match?
(武田)負けは弱さの証明ですか
Does losing prove that you're weak?
(武田)君たちにとて
負けは試練なんじゃないですか
Wouldn't you say that, to you guys, losing is like a trial by fire?
A test to see whether you can get back on your feet after crashing to the ground?
地に這いつくばたあと
また立て歩けるのかという
(武田)君たちが
そこに這いつくばたままならば
If you guys stay there, down on the ground, that really would prove you're weak.
それこそが弱さの証明です
We run laps convinced that we will all make it
We suffer through the nights for a vision we chose on a whim
Senseki                    Aoba Jousai
If you really want fairness then we'd all look basically the same
We will suffer through more nights for a vision instead of standing still
Our passion burns until the morning and we advance with closed eyes
I haven't forgotten you despite this passion
I run with only my headlight for guidance
No matter what awaits me I will laugh in this body I was born in
Is there someone running with your taillight for guidance?
What you call determination just means bunching up
Is someone going to follow up on all these impressions?
Will vowing to never falter let me laugh again?
よしじゃあ飯行くぞ
もちろんおごりだ
Okay, let's go eat.
My treat, of course.
(澤村)え飯すか
What? Eat, sir? But...
いやでも
(繋心)いいから食うんだよ
Just do as I say, and eat.
Closed
Sit Tavern
(繋心)おばちゃん悪い開店前に
(おばちゃん)なぁんの
Sorry to do this to you right before closing, Ma'am.
Think nothing of it!
This used to be the norm for you, remember?
こんなの前は
しょちゅうだたじゃないの
(繋心)
走たりとか跳んだりとか
All that running and jumping puts stress on the muscles and tears the muscle fiber.
筋肉に負荷がかかれば
筋繊維が切れる
試合後の今なんか
筋繊維ブチブチだ
At the end of a match, your muscle fibers will be in tatters.
You recover by eating.
(繋心)それを飯食て修復する
そうやて筋肉がつく
That's how you build muscle.
That's how you get stronger.
そうやて強くなる
だから食えちゃんとした飯をな
So eat up.
Eat a proper meal.
いただきます
Thank you for the food.
(一同)いただきます
はいどうぞ
Thank you for the food.
Please, dig in.
いただきます
Thank you for the food.
≪食え食え≫
Eat.
(繋心)≪少しずつでも確実に
Slowly...
but surely.
(繋心)≪強くなれ≫
Get stronger.
Next Episode Preview
Ukai, I'll cover this.
(武田)烏養君ここは僕が
(繋心)いいてことよ
Don't sweat it!
Hey, Ma'am! Check, please!
おうおばちゃんお勘定
(おばちゃん)はいよこんだけ
Here you go. I gave you a discount.
まけといたよ
(繋心)サンキュげ
Thanks!
Ugh! Those guys really packed it away!
あいつら結構食たじゃねぇか
Next time on Haikyuu!!:
Episode Twenty-five:
The Third Day
"The Third Day."